A Guide to John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part Four: Printed Matter from Magazines, Newspapers, and Books (Box 9)
  - "POE AT WEST POINT," unsigned [ Thomas W. Gibson ], 1867 November.; [543]; Pp. 754-756 clipped from Harper's (Box 10)
    Gibson had been a classmate of Poe at West Point. Item is annotated by Ingram.
  - "THE LATE N. P. WILLIS, AND LITERARY MEN FORTY YEARS AGO," unsigned, 1868 January.; [544]; Pp. 234-242 clipped from the Northern Monthly (Box 10)
    Item accompanied by note by Thomas Ollive Mabbott, 3 April 1965, 1 p. Ingram was of the opinion that Thomas Cottrell Clarke was the author of this article, but in 1965 Professor Mabbott disputed him, declaring that Major Mordecai M. Noah had written it. Mabbott, however, made no attempt to explain why the publisher had waited nearly twenty years after Noah's death to print the item.
  - "EVENINGS WITH THE AUTHOR OF'OLD GRIMES'," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1868 March 27.; [545]; 1/4 column clipped from the Providence Journal (Box 10)
    Mrs. Whitman describes evenings spent with distinguished company in the home of Albert G. Greene in Providence and discusses Sarah Margaret Fuller's conversation.
  - "A DEAD MAN DEFENDED: BEING SOME REMINISCENCES OF THE POET POE," by Captain Mayne Reid, 1869 April.; [546]; Pp. 305-308 of Onward (Box 10)
  - "POE'S'EUREKA' AND RECENT SPECULATIONS," by William Hand Browne, 1869 August.; [547]; Pp. 190-199 clipped from the New Eclectic Magazine, V (Box 10)
  - "THE ROUT OF THE CHILDREN," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1870 March 24.; [548]; 6 stanzas clipped from the Providence Journal, p. 1 (Box 10)
    The poem is from Victor Hugo's "A Des Oiseaux Envolves."
  - "OUR HAUNTED ROOM," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1870 April 25.; [548-a]; 17 3-line stanzas clipped from the Providence Journal, p. 1 (Box 10)
  - "SOUTHERN LITERATURE," unsigned, 1870 June 8.; [549]; 1 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 10)
    Writer furnishes a nasty picture of Poe in the course of criticizing Southern literature. The item may be the work of Kate Field.
  - "THE PORTRAIT," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1870 July 2.; [549-a]; 10 4-line stanzas clipped from the Providence Journal, p. 1, which reprints from Old and New for July (Box 10)
    In forwarding this clipping to Ingram in 1874, Mrs. Whitman wrote in the margin: "You must not think that this is a literal transcript from any canvas but rather from a picture seen in the mind's eye[,] Horatio."
  - "DID POE WRITE'THE RAVEN' ?" by Reverend J. Shaver, and "POE'S POEM OF'THE RAVEN'," by "J.", 1870 July 29.; [550]; 3/4 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 10)
    The J. Shaver item is a letter to the New Orleans Times claiming to have found a letter to a Mr. Daniels of Philadelphia in which Poe admits stealing "The Raven" from Samuel Fenwick. The "J" item is a letter, pasted on a sheet with the first, from a purported classmate of Poe to the Editor of the Richmond Dispatch denying the charge.
  - "LITERARY RETROSPECTIONS," by William Leggett, 1870 December 10.; [552]; 2 columns clipped from the New York Evening Mail (Box 10)
    Article prints comments upon Poe, William Leggett, John J. Audubon, John Howard Payne, McDonald Clarke, Aaron Burr, Edwin Forrest, and Fanny Kemble made by the late William Gowans in his "Western Memorabilia."
  - "POE'S GUARDIAN ANGEL," by James Wood Davidson, 1870 April 21.; [555]; 3/4 column clipped from the Home Journal, p. 1 (Box 10)
    Obituary of Maria Clemm, who died on 16 February 1871.
  - "THE AMERICAN CRITIC," by Eugene Benson, 1870 August.; [556]; 1/2 column clipped from the Season (Box 10)
    A severe summing up of Poe as a critic. The item is annotated by both Sarah Helen Whitman and Ingram.
  - "THE CHIMES DONE IN RHYMES. AFTER POE AND NEWMAN," by "D. P.", 1870 November 26.; [557]; 4 stanzas. 1/2 column clipped from the Capital (Box 10)
  - "THE GRAVE OF POE," by Eugene L. Didier, 1872 January 27.; [558]; Clipped from Appleton's Journal, p. 104. With a 11/2 column reprint of portions of this article in an unidentified Washington, DC, newspaper. (Box 10)
  - "A STORY ABOUT EDGAR A. POE, " unsigned, 1872 April.; [559]; 1/4 column reprint in an unidentified newspaper of "Monthly Gossip" in Lippincott's Magazine, May 1872 (Box 10)
    An account attributed to John R. Thompson of Poe's drinking a glass of brandy at one swallow after having previously drunk thirteen mint juleps.
  - "MORE ABOUT POE. HOW'ANNABEL LEE' CAME TO BE PUBLISHED," by " Paul Peebles ", 1872 May 8.; [560]; 3/4 column clipped from the Home Journal, p. 1 (Box 10)
    In return for a loan of $5, Poe allegedly flung the MS. of "Annabel Lee" to John R. Thompson, remarking that it was "a little thing I knocked off last night --it's not much."
  - "HOW POE'S'ANNABEL LEE' CAME TO BE PUBLISHED", 1872 May 8.; [560-a]; 1/4 column reprint of the Home Journal item clipped from the Providence Evening Press (Box 10)
    Same as Item 560.
  - "A GRAND POEM," unsigned, 1872 August.; [561]; Clipping from an unidentified newspaper. 1/2 column (Box 10)
    Reprints "Resurrexi," purportedly a posthumous poem by Poe delivered through the agency of the Spiritualist medium Lizzie Doten.
  - "SPIRIT POETRY," unsigned, 1872 ca. August.; [561-a]; Clipping from unidentified publication. 1 1/4 columns (Box 10)
    Reprints "The Kingdom," an imitation of "Ulalume" which is purportedly a posthumous poem by Poe delivered through the agency of the Spiritualist medium Lizzie Doten.
  - "TO PERDITA," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1872 ca. August.; [561-b]; 5 stanzas clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from Old and New for August, 1872, p. 184. (Box 10)
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE'S LAST DAYS," unsigned, 1872 September 21.; [562]; Pp. 371-372 clipped from Public Opinion, reprinted from Harper's New Monthly Magazine. 1/2 column. (Box 10)
  - "PORTRAITS OF POE," by Chandos Fulton, 1873 March 12.; [563]; 1/2 column clipped from the Home Journal, p. [1] (Box 10)
    Surveys both portraits and daguerreotypes of Poe.
  - "OUR LAST WALK," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1873 October 4.; [565]; 9 4-line stanzas clipped from the Providence Daily Journal (Box 10)
    The poem is addressed to "R. B. B."
  - "SANTA CLAUS," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1873 December 24.; [566]; 13 4-line stanzas clipped from the Providence Daily Journal. (Box 10)
  - "LITERARY MORCEAUX," unsigned, ca. 1873.; [567]; 1/2 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from the Augusta Constitutionalist (Box 10)
    Reports visit by Paul Hamilton Hayne to Poe's grave in Baltimore and his appeal for a monument to be erected over Poe's remains.
  - "THE LIFE AND CHARACTER OF EDGAR A. POE, " unsigned, ante 1874.; [568]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 10)
    Reports a lecture by John Reuben Thompson before the YMCA on Poe as a critic, a romancer, and a poet. Quotes from the close of the lecture.
  - ON ROSALIE POE, unsigned, 1874 February 16?.; [569]; 2 paragraphs separately clipped from unidentified newspapers (Box 10)
    One clipping reports from the Newark Advertiser that Poe's sister is residing in the utmost poverty at Hicks Landing on the James River in Virginia. The other clipping declares that she is now poor, aged, and helpless and is residing in Baltimore.
  - "MORE NEW FACTS ABOUT EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by John H. Ingram, 1874 February 21.; [570]; Pp. 248-250 clipped from the London Mirror (Box 11)
    These pages are the single known copy of this article which is based almost entirely upon information about Poe that Ingram had begun receiving from Sarah Helen Whitman in January 1874. He had previously published an article called "New Facts about Edgar Allan Poe " in the Mirror on 24 January 1874, but no known copy of it has survived.
  - ON ROSALIE POE, unsigned, 1874 ca. March.; [571]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Baltimore newspaper (Box 11)
    Reports Rosalie Poe's straitened circumstances and requests contributions of clothing and comforts of life to be sent to her at the Epiphany Church Home, Washington, DC.
  - "LES DEUX ASSASSINATS DE LA RUE MORGUE" ("THE MURDERS IN THE RUE MORGUE"), by Poe, 1874 April 18 & May 2.; [572]; Pp. 39-40, 42-44; 70-75 of Muse Universel, III-IV (Box 11)
    A "traduction nouvelle" accompanied by a grisly illustration.
  - "POE. HIS POETRY AND HIS GRAVE," unsigned, 1874 May 5.; [573]; 1/5 column clipped from the Baltimore Evening Post (Box 11)
    "B. G. T." inquires about the authorship of the opening lines to Poe's first "To Helen." In his reply, the Editor urges the inquirer to show his appreciation of Poe by helping to keep his neglected grave in order and adds that the Counting Room of the Post will receive subscriptions for that purpose.
  - "LITERARY NOTES," unsigned, 1874 ante May 14.; [574]; 3 paragraphs clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 11)
    An offer by George W. Childs of Philadelphia to erect a monument over Poe's grave has been declined by friends and relatives of the poet, who prefer that the memorial be the one proposed by the teachers and public school officials, as well as admirers of Poe in Baltimore, who have already placed a considerable sum for it in the hands of the proper committee.
  - "A MONUMENT TO POE," unsigned, 1874 May 17.; [575]; Paragraph clipped from the Baltimore Gazette, reprinted from the Baltimore Sun (Box 11)
    After describing the efforts by Paul Hamilton Hayne to raise money for the monument to Poe, the article offers a mixed account of Poe's character and genius.
  - "THE POE MONUMENT," unsigned, 1874 ca. May 18.; [576]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 11)
    It was Mr. J. C. Derby of Baltimore who suggested to George W. Childs that a suitable monument be erected over Poe's grave.
  - NOTICE OF THE PUBLICATION OF AN ARTICLE BY INGRAM, unsigned, 1874 June 6.; [577]; Paragraph clipped from the Academy (Box 11)
    Ingram's article appears in the Gentleman's Magazine for May and in the Temple Bar for June 1874.
  - "THE LONDON PRESS ON EDGAR ALLAN POE, " unsigned, 1874 June 30.; [578]; Paragraph clipped from the Providence Journal (Box 11)
    Calls attention to Ingram's article on Poe appearing in the Gentleman's Magazine for May and in the Temple Bar for June 1874.
  - "POE'S HOUSE AT FORDHAM, " by M. J. Lamb, 1874 July 18.; [579]; Pp. 75-77 clipped from Appleton's Journal, XI (Box 11)
    Lamb describes the Poe cottage and furnishes an illustration captioned "The House in which Poe Wrote 'The Raven'."
  - "LITERARY NOTES," unsigned, 1874 July 18.; [580]; Paragraph clipped from the Boston Commonwealth (Box 11)
    Item notes three upcoming lectures by William F. Gill, one of which is entitled "The Romance of Edgar A. Poe. "
  - "ADVENTURE INCOMPARABLE D'UN CERTAIN HANS PFAALL," by Poe, 1874 July 18.; [581]; Pp. 248-252 of Muse Universel, IV (Box 11)
    One installment of a translation of Poe's "Hans Pfaall" accompanied by an illustration of a balloon's ascent.
  - ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE DEATH OF ROSALIE POE, unsigned, 1874 July 22.; [582]; Paragraph clipped from the Washington Evening Star (Box 11)
    Rosalie Poe died in Epiphany Church Home in Washington on this date at 68 years of age.
  - "DEATH OF THE SISTER OF EDGAR ALLEN [sic] POE, " unsigned, 1874 July 23.; [583]; Paragraph clipped from the Washington Daily Critic (Box 11)
    Rosalie Poe came to the Epiphany Church Home on 1 March. Following her funeral on 23 July, she was buried at the Rock Creek Cemetery.
  - " EDGAR ALLEN [sic] POE, " unsigned, 1874 November 29.; [584]; 3/4 column clipped from the New York Herald (Box 11)
    A favorable review of Richard Henry Stoddard's new edition of Poe's poems.
  - "STODDARD'S EDITION OF POE," unsigned, 1874 December 8.; [585]; 2 columns clipped from the New York Daily Tribune (Box 11)
    A favorable review of the book and a censorious account of the "tragic" life of an "erratic genius." The clipping is annotated by Ingram.
  - A MEMORIAL OF LOUIS A. GODEY, 1874 December 15.; [586]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper (Box 11)
    John Scott of Pennsylvania presented before the Senate a memorial of the publisher of Godey's Lady's Book in which he set forth alleged unjust discriminations against periodicals in the new postage law.
  - "HOLIDAY BOOKS," unsigned, 1874 December 21.; [587]; 1 column clipped from the New York Herald (Box 11)
    Review of William F. Gill's article " Edgar Poe and His Biographer, Rufus W. Griswold, " in Lotos Leaves, Boston, 1875, pp. 279-306.
  - OBITUARY OF THOMAS COTTRELL CLARKE, unsigned, 1874 ca. December 23.; [588]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from Potter's American Monthly (Box 11)
    Clarke died in Camden, NJ, on 23 December 1874.
  - "LOST TO THE WORLD," unsigned, 1874 December 26.; [589]; 2 columns clipped from the Flushing Journal (Box 11)
    A sketch of Poe's life abounding in inaccurate details. Possibly the work of Dr. Roland S. Houghton.
  - " GEORGE W. CHILDS ERECTING A MONUMENT TO POE," unsigned, 1874.; [590]; Paragraph clipped from the New York Evening Post (Box 11)
    George W. Childs has offered to erect a suitable monument over Poe's grave, allowing the money already collected for one to be kept as a maintenance fund.
  - "WHAT BALTIMORE EDITORS THINK OF POE," unsigned, ca. 1874.; [591]; 1/2 column clipped from the New York Commercial Appeal (Box 11)
    Despite the report that three Baltimore editors deny genius to Poe and wish he had died and been buried somewhere else, Paul H. Hayne and George W. Childs still want to erect a monument over his grave in Baltimore.
  - AN INTERVIEW WITH INGRAM, unsigned, ca. 1874.; [592]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified London newspaper (Box 11)
    Ingram denies to an American correspondent that he intends to take to lecturing and that he is not going to make a lecture tour of the United States.
  - "THE MONUMENT TO EDGAR ALLAN POE, " unsigned, 1874?.; [593]; 1/2 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from the Baltimore American (Box 11)
    Funds for a monument are to be gathered by subscription and supplemented by a gift from George W. Childs of Philadelphia.
  - " EDGAR POE'S POEMS," unsigned, 1875 January 5.; [594]; 1 column clipped from a proof sheet of the Daily Review (Box 11)
    Review of Volume III, Poems and Essays, from The Works of Edgar Allan Poe, edited by Ingram and published by A. and C. Black, Edinburgh. The reviewer considers prose to have been Poe's "strength" and verse his "byework."
  - "PERSONALITIES," unsigned, 1875 January 28.; [595]; 1 column clipped from the Independent (Box 11)
    A slashing attack upon Poe and upon Moncure D. Conway's defense of him recently published in the Cincinnati Commercial Tribune.
  - REVIEW OF RICHARD HENRY STODDARD'S RECENT EDITION OF POE'S POEMS, unsigned, 1875 ca. January.; [596]; 1/2 column clipped from the Daily Graphic (Box 11)
  - "ROSALIE OR ROSE POE," by Erl Rygenhoeg, 1875 February.; [597]; Paragraph clipped from the American Bibliopolist, VII, p. 18 (Box 11)
  - ENGLISH PRESS TEEMS WITH PRAISES FOR INGRAM'S NEW AND COMPLETE EDITION OF POE'S WORK, unsigned, 1875 ca. February.; [598]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Richmond newspaper. (Box 11)
  - "ROSALIE, OR ROSE POE," by S. H. K., 1875 March 4.; [599]; Paragraph clipped from the American Bibliopolist (Box 11)
    In answer to Erl Rygenhoeg's comments [Item 597], "S. H. K." of Washington, DC, writes that Miss Poe herself had doubtless furnished her name to the Epiphany Church Home authorities as "Rose" and not "Rosalie."
  - REVIEW OF RICHARD HENRY STODDARD'S NEW EDITION OF POE'S POEMS, unsigned, 1875 March 9.; [600]; Paragraph clipped from the Providence Journal (Box 11)
    The reviewer believes that Stoddard's Memoir of Poe adds something of interest to the volume but that Poe's poems need no praise, for they will live forever on the lips and in the hearts of his readers.
  - "MEMORIES OF POE," unsigned, 1875 March 10.; [600-a]; 1/2 column clipped from the Home Journal, p. [4] (Box 11)
    Comments upon an article about Poe written by Moncure D. Conway.
  - MENTION OF INGRAM'S ARTICLE, " EDGAR A. POE " IN THE ECLECTIC FOR MARCH, unsigned, 1875 March.; [601]; Paragraph clipped from the Boston Commonwealth (Box 11)
    The commentator finds Ingram's article a compromise between Rufus W. Griswold's bitterness and Ingram's customary admiration.
  - MENTION OF INGRAM'S ARTICLE, " EDGAR A. POE, " WHICH IS TO APPEAR IN THE INTERNATIONAL REVIEW FOR MARCH, unsigned, 1875 March.; [602]; Paragraph clipped from the Boston Commonwealth (Box 11)
    The commentator labels Ingram's article a defense of Poe against Rufus W. Griswold's posthumous slanders.
  - "THE ORIGIN OF POE'S RAVEN," unsigned, 1875 April 14.; [602-a]; Paragraph clipped from the Home Journal (Box 11)
    The Athenaeum reports that Poe took the name "Lenore" and the burden "Nevermore" from two poems that Alfred, Lord Tennyson had published in The Gem in 1831.
  - OBITUARY OF COLONEL GAMALIEL LYMAN DWIGHT, unsigned, 1875 April 21.; [603]; 1/4 column clipped from the Providence Journal (Box 11)
    Enclosed in Item 19. Colonel Dwight was a close personal friend of Sarah Helen Whitman.
  - DESCRIPTION OF MONUMENT TO BE ERECTED OVER POE'S GRAVE, by E. L. D. [ Eugene L. Didier ], 1875 May 15.; [604]; 11/2 columns clipped from "Editor's Table" of Appleton's Journal. (Box 11)
  - NOTICE OF LAUDATORY RECEPTION GIVEN BY THE ENGLISH PRESS TO INGRAM'S EDITION OF POE'S WORKS, unsigned, 1875 May 21.; [605]; Paragraph clipped from the Richmond Daily Enquirer. (Box 11)
  - NOTICE OF A LECTURE ON PSYCHOMETRY DELIVERED BY PROFESSOR JOSEPH RHODES BUCHANAN, unsigned, 1875 May 22.; [606]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified Boston newspaper (Box 11)
    The lecture was delivered at Parker Memorial Hall, Boston, on 2 April 1875. Pasted to this notice is another paragraph stating that Professor Buchanan had read a chapter of his forthcoming work, Philosophy and Philosophers, to a coterie of literary gentlemen assembled in his home in Louisville, KY. It was to Buchanan that Sarah Helen Whitman submitted her MS. of "To Helen" given to her by Poe, for a psychometric reading. He did not return the MS. to her, and it has never been located. See Items 241, 253, 262.
  - "SOMETHING ABOUT EDGAR A. POE, " unsigned, 1875 June 9.; [607]; Paragraphs clipped from the Baltimore Sun and the Richmond Evening Journal (Box 11)
    Reports Colonel Robert Mayo's memories of youthful swimming feats he shared with Poe in Richmond.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE, " by John Watson Dalby, 1875 August.; [608]; Pp. 473-487 clipped from St. James's Magazine, XXXVI (Box 11)
    A biographical-critical article based upon Ingram's four-volume edition of Poe's works. Dalby notes omissions and suggests needed changes to be made in the next edition.
  - "POE AND BYRON," unsigned, 1875 September 21.; [609]; 1 1/4 columns clipped from the Baltimore American (Box 11)
    The article compares the posthumous reputations of the two poets.
  - "SCRIBNER," unsigned, 1875 ca. September 27.; [610]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified New York newspaper (Box 11)
    The item notices the second installment of E. C. Stedman's "Minor Victorian Poets" in Scribner's Magazine and quotes with approval a long paragraph from Francis Gerry Fairfield's "A Madman of Letters," which was an essay on Poe published in Scribner's Monthly for October.
  - "GENIUS OF POE," unsigned, 1875 September 29.; [610-a]; 3 columns clipped from the Home Journal, p. [4] (Box 11)
    A biographical-critical article.
  - "AN EARLY POEM BY EDGAR ALLEN [sic] POE, " signed E. L. D. [ Eugene L. Didier ], 1875 September.; [611]; Pp. 607-608 clipped from Scribner's Monthly (Box 11)
    P. 607 carries a facsimile of what purports to be a holograph copy of "Alone," signed by Poe and dated 17 March 1829. Ingram's notation on it reads, "Not Poe's calligraphy."
  - MONUMENT TO BE ERECTED AT POE'S GRAVE IS TO BE SURMOUNTED BY A RAVEN IN MARBLE, unsigned, 1875 ca. September.; [612]; Paragraph clipped from an unidentified newspaper. (Box 11)
  - "POE," unsigned, 1875 October 8.; [614]; 3/4 column clipped from the New York World (Box 11)
    Eulogy evoked by the tardy honor done to Poe's ashes by the plans to erect a monument over his hitherto unmarked grave.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE, " unsigned, 1875 October 9.; [615]; 2 1/4 columns clipped from the Baltimorean (Box 11)
    Article is accompanied by a picture of Poe reproduced from a photograph by C. S. Mosher of Baltimore. On the obverse of this clipping there is a paragraph stating that the monument is already in place over Poe's grave.
  - "TO ISADORE. A POEM BY EDGAR ALLAN POE ", 1875 October 9?.; [616]; 5 10-line stanzas clipped from the Columbia Register [SC] (Box 11)
    These verses were written by Abijah M. Ide, Jr., of South Attleboro, MA, who sent them to Poe who printed them in the Broadway Journal in 1845. Because Poe's MS. copy survives, the poem has been proffered from time to time as Poe's own composition. See Item 678.
  - "DISINTERMENT OF THE REMAINS OF EDGAR A. POE, " unsigned, 1875 October 11.; [616-a]; Paragraph clipped from the Providence Daily Journal, p. 1, which reprints item from the Baltimore American (Box 11)
    Describes the condition of Poe's remains when exhumed.
  - "POETIC PORTRAITS," by Edgar Fawcett, 1875 October 12.; [617]; 1/3 column clipped from the Richmond Daily Enquirer (Box 11)
    Two sonnets in tribute to "Poe" and "Whittier."
  - " EDGAR A. POE'S MONUMENT," unsigned, 1875 October 12?.; [618]; 1/4 column clipped from an unidentified newspaper, reprinted from the Augusta Constitutionalist, June 1875 (Box 11)
    After describing the monument, the Constitutionalist takes credit for having given impetus to the movement to place it over Poe's remains, arguing that its story of Paul Hamilton Hayne's description of the neglected grave had been widely circulated and thereby brought to the attention of J. C. Derby, who in turn was instrumental in convincing George W. Childs, the Philadelphia philanthropist, to underwrite the expense of the monument.
  - "A REPLY TO MR. FAIRFIELD," by Sarah Helen Whitman, 1875 October 13.; [619]; 1 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 11)
    In this long letter to the Editor, dated 29 September 1875, Mrs. Whitman cuttingly refutes Francis Gerry Fairfield's arguments, published in Scribner's Monthly in October 1875, that Poe was an epileptic, a "madman of letters."
  - DR. ABRAHAM H. OKIE SUPPORTS SARAH HELEN WHITMAN'S DENIAL OF FRANCIS GERRY FAIRFIELD'S CHARGE THAT POE WAS AN EPILEPTIC, unsigned, 1875 post October 13.; [620]; Paragraph clipped from the Providence Journal (Box 11)
    Dr. Okie had attended Poe in Mrs. Whitman's home in Providence in October 1848.
  - " EDGAR ALLAN POE. A LETTER FROM FRANCIS GERRY FAIRFIELD ", 1875 October 18.; [621]; 1/4 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 11)
    In this weak reply to Sarah Helen Whitman's spirited defense of Poe, Fairfield publicly repents of his former admiration of the poet.
  - "THE POET NOT AN EPILEPTIC," by F. K. M. [Dr. Fred K. Marvin ], 1875 October 18.; [622]; 1/4 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 11)
    Marvin supports Sarah Helen Whitman's attack on Francis Gerry Fairfield's allegations against Poe.
  - "'THE BELLS' AND'ANNABEL LEE'," by John S. Hart, 1875 October 18.; [623]; 1/4 column clipped from the New York Tribune (Box 11)
    In this letter to the Editor of the Tribune, the former editor of Sartain's Magazine discusses the dates of Poe's writing "The Bells" and "Annabel Lee" and gives dates of the various MSS. of "The Bells," which Poe submitted to Sartain's.
  - "THE MONUMENT TO EDGAR ALLAN POE, " unsigned, 1875 October 28.; [624]; 1/2 column clipped from the New York Herald (Box 11)